A Finding Aid to the J. B. Neumann papers, 1905-1967, in the Archives of American Art AAA.neumjsra
Archives of American Art
J. B. Neumann papers
1905-1967
AAA.neumjsra
Archives of American Art
2.1 Linear feet 4 boxes
The papers of gallery director, art dealer and publisher Jsrael Ber Neumann (1887-1961) measure 2.1 linear feet and date from 1905 to 1967. The papers document Neumann's career as the director of galleries in Berlin and Munich, Germany (1910-1924) as well as the New Art Circle gallery in New York City (1924-1952). Neumann was a respected art dealer, publisher of Artlover periodical, founder of Gehenna Press, and frequent lecturer. Found within his papers are correspondence with artists and museums, writings, printed materials mostly comprised of exhibition catalogues, artwork, and photographic materials.
Neumann, J. B.(Jsrael Ber)
Biographical/Historical note
J. B. (Jsrael Ber) Neumann (1887-1961) was a gallery director, art dealer and publisher. After immigrating to the U.S., Neumann founded the New Art Circle Gallery in New York City. Before then, he had art galleries in Berlin, Munich, Dusseldorf and Bremen, Germany.
J. B. Neumann was born in Austria in 1887. His father was an oil and lumber dealer. Neumann initially studied business but later apprenticed to a book and picture dealer when he was nineteen. While working as a clerk in a large bookstore in London, Neumann had the opportunity to work at the rare book dealer’s table in the British Museum. The job allowed him to assess and handle fine and rare books, starting a lifelong passion, and Neumann went on to amass a substantial personal library.
In 1910, Neumann returned to Berlin, Germany and in 1911 opened a book and art shop where he exhibited the work of Edvard Munch and others. Neumann had many friends who were artists and in 1915-1916 he was secretary to the Berlin Secession, a prominent German artist association. By 1922 Neumann had branch offices in Bremen, Dusseldorf and Munich.
Neumann immigrated to America in 1923 and left the Berlin gallery to the directorship of Karl Nierendorf and the Munich gallery to Günther Franke. Neumann settled in New York City and one year later he opened a 57th Street gallery and bookshop, first called J.B. Neumann's Print Room and later the New Art Circle gallery. He supported numerous artists, including Wassily Kandinsky, Max Beckmann, Paul Klee, and Georges Rouault. Elsa Schmidt, Neumann’s wife, was an artist who worked in mosaics.
Neumann also worked as a publisher. He created the printing company Gehenna Press and published a series of periodicals including Bilderhefte (Berlin, 1920-1922) and Artlover (New York, 1926-1945, 1959). The New Art Circle gallery closed circa 1952 and, after working as its director for nearly three decades, Neumann became a consultant for museums and collectors. He was also a lecturer and he frequently spoke about art at universities, museums and galleries.
Neumann died in Rye, New York on April 28, 1961. He is survived by his widow, Elsa Schmid (d. 1970); two sons, Peter and Albrecht; and a daughter, Mrs. Johanna Lam.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of gallery director, art dealer and publisher Jsrael Ber Neumann (1887-1961) measure 2.1 linear feet and date from 1905 to 1967. The papers document Neumann's career as the director of galleries in Berlin and Munich, Germany (1910-1924) as well as the New Art Circle gallery in New York City (1924-1952). Neumann was a respected art dealer, publisher of Artlover periodical, founder of Gehenna Press, and frequent lecturer. Found within his papers are correspondence with artists and museums, writings, printed materials mostly comprised of exhibition catalogues, artwork, and photographic materials.
Correspondence is between Neumann and friends, colleagues, and museums. There is also correspondence with notable artists, including Josef Albers, Leonard Baskin, Max Beckmann, Wassily Kandinsky, and Abraham Rattner, among others. There are also condolence letters from friends and colleagues to Elsa Schmid, Neumann's wife.
Scattered writings consist of typescript drafts of Neumann's speeches and one article on expressionism. There is also one speech written by curator Richard Klein.
Printed materials comprise the bulk of the collection and include a bound gallery guest register, a disbound scrapbook, exhibition catalogs and announcements, brochures, magazines, posters, and news clippings. There are many exhibition catalogs from Neumann’s galleries in Berlin and Munich as well as from the New Art Circle gallery in New York. Artwork consists of two etchings and one drawing by an unknown artist or artists.
Photographic materials include black and white photographs and negatives, including notable portraits of Neumann by photographers Helen Balfour Morrison, Clarence White, and Hans Namuth.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 5 series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1925-1961 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Writings, 1919, 1954-circa 1960 (5 folders; Box 1)
Series 3: Printed Materials, 1910-1967 (1.7 linear feet; Box 1-4)
Series 4: Artwork, 1919-circa 1960 (3 folders; Box 3-4)
Series 5: Photographic Materials, 1905-circa 1950 (0.2 linear feet; Box 3-4)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of the collection are also available on 35 mm microfilm reels NJBN 1; N69/93-94; 3533; and 3947. While the microfilm is available for consultation at Archives of American Art offices, affliate centers, and through interlibrary loan, researchers are advised that the microfilm does not reflect the current order of the papers as described in this finding aid and may not be complete.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The J.B. Neumann papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in several installments between 1973-2007 by Eva Lee (family friend), Joy Weber, Max Weber's daughter, Neil Richmond, and Hellie Neumann, J.B. Neumann's granddaughter. Additional materials were loaned for microfilming in 1966-1967 by Neumann's wife Elsa Schmid.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives of American Art also holds a collection of Josef Albers letters to J. B. Neumann, 1934-1947 on microfilm reel 911.
Additional J.B. Neumann papers are also located at the Museum of Modern Art in New York. The museum microfilmed a portion of these papers and donated a copy of that film to the Archives. This material may be viewed on reel NJBN5 at Archives of American Art offices, affliate centers, and via interlibrary loan.
Separated Materials note
Also found in the Archives are papers that were lent for microfilming on Reels NJBN 1-4, most of which were not included in subsequent donations, except for papers relating Wassily Kandisky and correspondence with Leonard Baskin. These papers are not described in the container list of the finding aid and are available only on microfilm available in Archives of American Art offices, affliate centers, and for interlibrary loan. These papers include correspondence with numerous artists, art critics, museum directors, and many others. A list of correspondents is available in Archives of American Art offices by request.
Albers, Josef; Artlover.; Baskin, Leonard, 1922-2000; Beckmann, Max, 1884-1950; Gehenna Press.; Kandinsky, Wassily, 1866-1944; Morrison, Helen Balfour; Namuth, Hans; New Art Circle (New York, N.Y.); Rattner, Abraham; Schmid, Elsa, 1897-; White, Clarence H., 1871-1925, photographer; Art dealers--New York (State)--New York; Art galleries, Commercial -- New York (State) -- New York; Art, Modern--20th century--United States--History; Art--Periodicals; Drawings; Etchings; Gallery directors--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Scrapbooks
- Correspondence, 1925-1961; Series 1; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains a mixture of personal and professional correspondence between J. B. Neumann and his friends, colleagues, and museums. There is also scattered correspondence with artists, including Josef Albers, Leonard Baskin, Max Beckmann, Wassily Kandinsky, Abraham Rattner, and Georges Rouault. Correspondence with museums and galleries concerns Neumann's proposal for a German Expressionism exhibition. There are letters of condolence to Elsa Schmid, Neumann's wife, from friends and colleagues.
  - Albers, Josef, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Baskin, Leonard, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Beckmann, Max, 1925-1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - German Expressionism Exhibition, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Kandinsky, Nina, 1936-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Kandinsky, Wassily, 1935-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Klee, Felix, 1952-1956; 1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rattner, Abraham, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rouault, Georges, circa 1930-1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Thompson, G. D., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Valentiner, W. R., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Condolence Letters to Elsa Schmid, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Writings, 1919; 1954-circa 1960; Series 2; 5 Folders Box 1
  Writings consist primarily of scattered typescript drafts of speeches by Neumann for various occasions. There is a memorial speech for Curt Valentin, an introductory speech for artist Max Beckmann, and what appears to be a brief untitled speech about retiring and making his personal art collection available for viewing. There is also a typescript draft of a speech by Richard Klein, a curator and director who attributes his success to Neumann.
  - Brief Article on Expressionism, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Typescript Draft of Obituary for Curt Valentin, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Typescript Draft of Speech "How J. B. N. Started My Career" by Robert Klein, circa 1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Typescript Draft of Speech about Max Beckmann, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Typescript Draft of Untitled Retirement Speech, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    This is a typescript draft of a short speech after J. B. Neumann's retirement as director of the New Art Circle gallery in which he appears to be making his personal collection of art available for viewing during an exhibition.
- Printed Materials, 1910-1967; Series 3; 1.7 Linear feet Box 1-4
  Printed materials include a bound gallery guest register, a disbound scrapbook, exhibition catalogs and announcements, brochures, magazines, posters, and news clippings. Most of the printed materials consist of exhibition catalogs from Neumann’s galleries in Berlin and Munich, Germany and the New Art Circle gallery in New York. Exhibition catalogs from other galleries and museum, such as World House Galleries, are also included.
  - Guest book, 1929-1935 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Disbound Scrapbook, 1925-1934 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Disbound Scrapbook, 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Disbound Scrapbook, 1951-1957 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Disbound Scrapbook Undated Pages, 1925-1957 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Berlin Art Gallery Exhibition Catalogs, 1910-circa 1922 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 1.
  - Munich Art Gallery Exhibition Catalogs, 1927-1931 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 2.
  - New Art Circle Exhibition Catalogs, 1924-1951 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Neumann-Willard Gallery Exhibition Catalogs, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - J. B. Neumann at World House Galleries Bound Exhibition Catalog, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - World House Galleries Exhibition Catalogs, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - World House Galleries Bound Edition of Exhibition Catalogues, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - World House Galleries Exhibition Catalog Bound Edition, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Exhibition Catalogs for Assorted Galleries and Museums, bulk 1931-1958; 1931-1958; 1967 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - New Art Circle Exhibition Announcements, 1924-1932 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - New Art Circle Exhibition Announcements, 1934-1943 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - New Art Circle Exhibition Announcements, 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - New Art Circle Exhibition Announcements, 1950-1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Sales and Auction Catalogs, 1936-1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Maxim Karolik Estate Auction Catalog, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Archiv J. B. Neumann Auction Catalog, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - J. B. Neumann Lecture Invitations and Announcements, 1934-circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Brochures, circa 1925-circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Artlover: J. B. Neumann's Bilderhefte Anthology, Volume III, circa 1924-circa 1936 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Artlover Issues, circa 1926-circa 1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Artlover Library, Volumes 1, 2 and 5, circa 1926-circa 1945 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Americana, February, April, May, July Issues, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Americana, January-June Issues, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Art Front, 1936 March (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - New Masses, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - New Masses, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Booklets, circa 1955 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Articles, circa 1929-circa 1934 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - News Clippings, circa 1931 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - News Clippings about J. B. Neumann, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - J. B. Neumann Obituary, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Max Beckmann Sales Records, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Neumann's Gallery Georges Rouault Exhibition Poster, circa 1923-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 3.
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art Fellowship Certificate, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 4.
  - Guggenheim Museum Press Release, circa 1966 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Oversized Berlin Art Gallery Exhibition Catalog, 1910-circa 1922 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 23.
  - Oversized Munich Art Gallery Exhibition Catalog, 1927-1931 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 24.
  - Oversized Georges Rouault Exhibition Poster, circa 1923-circa 1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 12.
  - Oversized Metropolitan Museum of Modern Art Certificate, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 13.
- Artwork, 1919-circa 1960; Series 4; 3 Folders Box 3-4
  This series contains two etchings and one drawing. All three peices depict black and white sketches of faces, one of which appears to be an image of J. B. Neumann. Each artwork is signed by the artist, but the names are illegible.
  - Etching, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - J. B. Neumann Etching, circa 1920-circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 5. The etching might be of Neumann. There are a few illegible annotations and the artist signature below the etching and the words "Kunsthandler (art dealer) J. B. Neumann" written on the bottom left corner of the paper.
  - Drawing, circa 1940-circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 6.
  - Oversized J. B. Neumann Etching, circa 1920-circa 1960 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 16.
  - Oversized Drawing, circa 1940-circa 1960 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 17.
- Photographic Materials, 1905-circa 1950; Series 5; 0.2 Linear feet Box 3-4
  Photographic materials include black & white photographs and negatives. Most of the photographs are portraits of Neumann by photographers Helen Balfour Morrison, Clarence White, and Hans Namuth. There are also negatives of a few announcements and brochures which can also be found in printed materials series. Other miscellaneous photographs include a photograph of Edvard Munch and a portrait of Neumann and his wife Elsa Schmid.
  - Edvard Munch, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Willy Jaeckel's Painting of J. B. Neumann, circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - J. B. Neumann Portraits by Clarence H. White, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - J. B. Neumann and Serge Koussevitzky, circa 1930 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - J. B. Neumann and Elsa Schmid, circa 1930 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 7.
  - J. B. Neumann Portraits by Helen Balfour-Morrison, circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 8.
  - J. B. Neumann Portrait by Hans Namuth, circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 9.
  - Negatives of Exhibition Announcements and Brochures, circa 1920-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Oversized Photograph of J. B. Neumann and Elsa Schmid, circa 1930 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 22.
  - Oversized J. B. Neumann Portraits by Helen Balfour-Morrison, circa 1950 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 23.
  - Oversized J. B. Neumann Portrait by Hans Namuth, circa 1950 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 24.